Guide to the Missoula New Party Records 1992-2003
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Missoula New Party Records
1992-2003
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana-Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/ library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 825
New Party (Missoula, Mont.)
6.75 linear feet and 16 electronic files
672 kilobytes of digital materials
The Missoula New Party was a progressive political organization formed in the spring of 1993 by a group of Missoula, Montana citizens who were motivated to move the political system in a more progressive direction by creating a third party option to the existing two party system. Materials in this collection document the organization’s main functions and activities, including electoral campaigns at the local and state level, as well as a number of issue-based campaigns directing at changing policy. The records in the collection document the relationship between the local chapter and the national New Party organization, local grassroots efforts to engage and grow a third political party movement, and significant issues in progressive politics during the 1990s.
Historical Note
The Missoula New Party was a progressive political organization formed in the spring of 1993 by a group of Missoula citizens who were motivated to move the political system in a more progressive direction by creating a third party option to the existing two party system. As a local chapter of the national New Party, whose headquarters were located in New York, NY, the Missoula New Party embraced many of the national organization’s guiding principles including electoral reform through electoral fusion. Electoral fusion is a practice in which a candidate receives nominations from more than one political party and can occupy multiple ballot lines. This practice provides an alternative to the notion that third parties function as election spoilers by taking votes away from major party candidates.
One of the organization’s main activities was promoting and supporting the election campaigns of New Party members to local entities including city councils, school boards, and county boards, as well as other local and state level entities. During the mid-1990s multiple New Party members were successfully elected to city council as a result of the New Party’s grassroots campaigning efforts. Other activities included issue-based campaigns, most significantly a Living Wage campaign, which resulted in the city council passing of a living wage ordinance. Other issue-based campaigns included affordable housing, occupancy standards, and smart growth management.
In 1997, a United States Supreme Court decision rejected the New Party’s argument that electoral fusion was a right protected by the first amendment, effectively allowing state legislatures to legally ban electoral fusion as a practice. This significantly impacted the organization’s underlying principle, and led to the eventual dissolution of local New Party chapters around the country, including the Missoula New Party in 2001.
The collection consists of administrative, correspondence, financial, legal, publications, press clippings, and planning records generated and/or collected by the Missoula New Party during the organization’s existence. Materials in this collection document the organization’s main functions and activities, including electoral campaigns at the local and state level, as well as a number of issue-based campaigns directing at changing policy. The records in the collection document the relationship between the local chapter and the national New Party organization, local grassroots efforts to engage and grow a third political party movement, and significant issues in progressive politics during the 1990s.
The collection is divided into five series:
Series I: Administrative, 1.5 linear feet and 15 electronic files, 1992-2001
Series II: Campaigns, 1.5 linear feet, 1994- 2001
Series III: Elections, 2.25 linear feet and 1 electronic file, 1993-2001
Series IV: Publicity and Publications, 0.5 linear feet, 1994-2001
Series V: National New Party, 1.0 linear feet, 1993-2003
Series VI: Artifacts, 2 items,undated
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Materials were in custody of Missoula New Party members until transfer to the Archives.
Collection materials were acquired through two donations. The first donation of materials from Jim Fleischmann was acquired in May 2004. A second donation by Judy Smith on behalf of the Missoula New Party was acquired in June 2004.
The Missoula New Party Oral History Project (OH 400) at the Mansfield Library Archives and Special Collections contains audio recordings and transcripts of interviews conducted with four former members of the Missoula New Party.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Missoula (Mont.)--Politics and government--20th century
Political parties--Montana--Missoula; Political participation--Montana--Missoula; Elections--Montana--Missoula; Living wage movement--Montana--Missoula
Politics and Politicians; Montana
- Administrative Activities, 1992-2001; Series I; 1.5 linear feet and 15 electronic files; 640 kilobytes of digital materials
  This series contains materials related to the administrative activities of the Missoula New Party, including annual reports, outreach efforts, fundraising events, financial records, meeting minutes, training materials, media relations, membership, interns, student chapter documents, and governance documents. The Series has been divided into thirteen subseries based on specific administrative functions and activities.
  - Annual Meetings, 1997-2001; Subseries 1; 0.2 linear feet and 1 electronic file; 32 kilobytes of digital material
    - Annual Meeting, 1999 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Annual Meeting, 2000 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Annual Meeting, 2001 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Membership and Fundraising Reports, 1997 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Annual Meeting Notes, 1997 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Canvass, 1995-2001; Subseries 2; 0.1 linear feet
    - Canvasser Training, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Canvass, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Canvass, 1997 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Canvass, 1999 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Canvass Rap, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Canvass, 2001 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Coalition and Outreach Efforts, undated; Subseries 3; 0.1 linear feet
    - High School Presentations, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Human Rights Network, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Progressive Missoula, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Media clippings, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Questions for Coalition Partners, undated (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Committees - Local, 1994-2001; Subseries 4; 0.1 linear feet and 2 electronic files; 64 kilobytes of digital material
    - Agendas, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Committee Structure, undated (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Minutes, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Minutes, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Steering Committee Notes, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Database Subcommittee, 1999 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Committees List, 1997 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Steering Committee Meeting Agenda, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Financial Records, 1996-1999; Subseries 5; 0.1 linear feet and 1 electronic file; 32 kilobytes of digital material
    - Financial Reports, 1996 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Financial Reports, 1997 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Financial Reports, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Financial Documents, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Montana People's Action Invoice, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Fundraising Events, 1998-2000; Subseries 6; 0.1 linear feet and 3 electronic files; 128 kilobytes of digital material
    - Hightower Banquet, 1998 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Hightower Banquet, 2000 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - New Party Party, 1999 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Other Fundraising Ideas, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Progressive Missoula Awards Banquet Letter, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Progressive Missoula Awards Banquet Invitation, undated (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Progressive Missoula Awards Banquet Recipients, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Governance, 1993-2000; Subseries 7; 0.2 linear feet and 2 electronic files; 128 kilobytes of digital material
    - Action Plan, 1996 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Action Plan, 1997 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - Action Plan, 2000 (Box-folder 1/32)
    - Bundling, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 1/33)
    - Employment contracts, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/34)
    - Expansion Bozeman, Butte, Helena, 1997 (Box-folder 1/35)
    - Hoffman, Jim's dissociation, 1999 (Box-folder 1/36)
    - Union Hall Rental Agreement, undated (Box-folder 1/37)
    - Bylaws, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1/38)
    - Charter, 1997 (Box-folder 1/39)
    - Mission Statement, 1993 (Box-folder 1/40)
    - Progressive Agenda / Proposals, 1998 (Box-folder 1/41)
    - Principles, 1997 (Box-folder 1/42)
    - Commissioner of Political Practices Reports, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 1/43)
    - Action Plan, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Principles, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Interns, 1996-1999; Subseries 8; 0.1 linear feet
    - Interns Description, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1/44)
    - Interns, 1999 (Box-folder 1/45)
  - Media Relations, 1996-2001; Subseries 9; 0.1 linear feet
    - Committee Media, 1996 (Box-folder 1/46)
    - Info about Media, undated (Box-folder 1/47)
    - Press Releases, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 1/48)
    - Radio / TV, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 1/49)
    - Strategy, 1997 (Box-folder 1/50)
    - Strategy, 1999 (Box-folder 1/51)
    - Spin Media Training, undated (Box-folder 1/52)
  - Membership, 1994-2001; Subseries 10; 0.2 linear feet and 4 electronic files; 128 kilobytes of digital material
    - House Visit Form, undated (Box-folder 1/53)
    - Member Lists, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 1/54)
    - Phone Polls, 1996 (Box-folder 1/55)
    - Forms, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Living Wage Dessert Party Ward 6, 1999 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Membership Renewals, 1996 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Plan, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Renewal Letters, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Renewal Phone Raps, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Reporting Documents, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Sustainer Info and Data, 1996 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Women's Leadership Project, 1999 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Houseparty Project, 1996 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - House Parties Attendees, 1996 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - House Party Invites, 1996 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Houseparties, 1997 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - General Membership Meeting Agenda, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - New Member Phone Rap, 1997 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Renewal Phone Rap, 1997 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - House Party Invitation, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Organizer, 1992-2000; Subseries 11; 0.1 linear feet and 2 electronic files; 128 kilobytes of digital material
    - Advertisements / Fliers, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Contracts, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Evaluations, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Job Description, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Work Plans Organizer, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Action Education, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Campaign Planning, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 2/20)
    - 2 Year Planning Documents, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - Committee Meetings Running Meetings, 1998 (Box-folder 2/22)
    - Community Action School Workbook, undated (Box-folder 2/23)
    - Consensus Training / Active Listening, 1992 (Box-folder 2/24)
    - Elections / Campaign Training, 1999 (Box-folder 2/25)
    - House Visits, 1999 (Box-folder 2/26)
    - Mid-Level Organizers Training, 1999 (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Overview, undated (Box-folder 2/28)
    - Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Office Administration Instructions, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
    - Organizer Resignation, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
  - Student Chapter, 2001; Subseries 12; 0.1 linear feet
    - ASUM, 2000 (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Budget Request, 2001 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - Fliers, undated (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Governing Documents, undated (Box-folder 2/33)
    - Organizational Meetings, 2001 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - Students (Interested), undated (Box-folder 2/35)
- Campaigns, 1994-2001; Series II; 1.5 linear feet
  This series contains materials generated in relation to campaigns organized around specific political issues. Materials include research materials, correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, and outreach materials. The series is divided into four subseries.
  - Issue Campaigns, 1994-2001; Subseries 1; 0.5 linear feet
    - Corporate Responsibility, 1996 (Box-folder 2/36)
    - Energy Issues, 2001 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - Family Definition Campaign, undated (Box-folder 2/38)
    - Housing - Accessory Dwelling Units, undated (Box-folder 2/39)
    - Housing Affordable City Council Meetings, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2/40)
    - Housing Affordable 2001 Housing Pains Study (Box-folder 2/41)
    - Human Rights, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/42)
    - Local Government Review Study Commission, 1994 (Box-folder 2/43)
    - School Closure, 1994-2000 (Box-folder 2/44)
    - Smart Growth, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/45)
    - Sustainable Cities Project, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 2/46)
    - Complaint to Political Practices, 1997 (Box-folder 2/47)
    - Propaganda, 1998 (Box-folder 2/48)
    - Response to CFCG, 1997 (Box-folder 2/49)
  - Living Wage, 1995-2001; Subseries 2; 0.5 linear feet
    - Bibliography, 1999 (Box-folder 2/50)
    - Business Support, 1999 (Box-folder 2/51)
    - Canvass Living Wage Ward 1, 1999 (Box-folder 2/52)
    - Canvass Ward 3, 1999 (Box-folder 2/53)
    - Canvass Living Wage Ward 6, 1999 (Box-folder 2/54)
    - City Council Reports, 1996 (Box-folder 2/55)
    - City Council Testifiers, undated (Box-folder 2/56)
    - Coalition Agenda, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 2/57)
    - Coalition Partners, 2000 (Box-folder 2/58)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 2/59)
    - Factsheets / Fliers, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2/60)
    - Federal Living Wage Legislation, 2000 (Box-folder 2/61)
    - Initiative Language, 1999 (Box-folder 2/62)
    - Initiative Timeline and Goals, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/63)
    - Job Gap Study, 1999 (Box-folder 2/64)
    - Letter (LTE, City council people, etc.), 1999-2001 (Box-folder 2/65)
    - News Articles Missoula, 1999 (Box-folder 2/66)
    - News Articles National, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 2/67)
    - Ordinance - Final, undated (Box-folder 2/68)
    - Ordinance Proposals, 1999 (Box-folder 2/69)
    - Other cities Campaigns, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 2/70)
    - Other cities Successes, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 2/71)
    - Other cities Studies, 1996 (Box-folder 2/72)
    - Petition Signers who voted, 2001 (Box-folder 2/73)
    - Press Advisories, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2/74)
    - Responses to Living Wage Concerns, 1999 (Box-folder 2/75)
    - Raps, undated (Box-folder 2/76)
    - Steering Committee, 2000 (Box-folder 2/77)
  - Campaign Finance Reform, 1996-2001; Subseries 3; 0.25 linear feet
    - Montana Campaign Finance Reform Int. / Voting History, 1997 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Lawyers, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Coalition Individuals and Groups, 1998 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Needed Changes, 1998 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - General Studies and Articles, 1998 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Other State and Local Campaign Finance Reform Work, 1997 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Federal Campaign Finance Reform, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    - National New Party Communications, 1998 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Missoula Campaign Finance Reform Campaign History, 1997 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Montana Law, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Campaign Finance Reform, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Fusion, 1996-2001; Subseries 4; 0.25 linear feet
    - Fusion, 1996-2001 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Ballot Initiative 1998 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Fliers, undated (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Supreme Court Decision, 1996 (Box-folder 3/15)
- Elections, 1993-2001; Series III; 0.5 linear feet and 1 electronic file; 32 kilobytes of digital material
  This series contains materials related to local and statewide elections, including city council, school board, and state representative elections. Materials include campaign literature, press clippings, and Missoula New Party Elections Committee documents.
  - Campaign Brochures, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Candidate Search, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Demarinis, Naomi, 1999 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Handler, Allison Ward 2, 2001 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Harmon, Dave Ward 1, 1997 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Herbig, Lois Ward 1, 1999 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - McGrath, Jim Ward 2, 1999 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Press Clippings Elections, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Sweet, Craig Ward 6, 1997 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Torma, John Ward 3, 1999 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Tracy, Linda Ward 2, 1997 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Missoula Neighborhood Council Map, 2001 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Accountability Partnership, 2001 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Erickson, Ron State Rep., 2000 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Gutsche, Gail State Rep., 2000 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Results Elections, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - School Board, 2001 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Elections Committee, 1998 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Elections Committee, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Timelines, 1998 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - Candidate Screening, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Candidates, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 3/37)
  - Campaign Yard Signs and Ward Map, 2001 and undated (Box OS 6)
  - Missoula Precinct Map 2001 (Box OS 7)
  - List of Potential Candidates, 1998 (Electronic file Electronic File)
- Publicity & Publications, 1994-2001; Series IV; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contain publicity and published articles about the Missoula New Party and newsletters published by the Missoula New Party chapter. The Series has been divided into two Subseries.
  - Press Clippings, 1996-1997; Subseries 1; 0.1 linear feet
    - Clippings, 1996 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Clippings, 1997 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - New Party News Clippings, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Newsletters - Local, 1994-2001; Subseries 2; 0.4 linear feet
    - Local newsletters, 1994 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Local newsletters, 1995 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Local newsletters, 1996 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Local newsletters, 1997 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Local newsletters, 1998 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Local newsletters, 1999 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Local newsletters, 2000 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Local newsletters, 2001 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Flyers and Posters, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    - New Party - 3.5 inch Floppy Disk, undated (Box-folder 4/53)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
- National New Party, 1993-2003; Series V; 1.0 linear feet
  This series contains materials documenting the relationship between the Missoula New Party chapter and the National New Party organization, including correspondence, annual meetings, national newsletters, and other state chapters.
  - Constitution, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Governance, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
  - News Articles 3rd Party, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - News Articles, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Other chapters, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Policies, 1996 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Principles, undated (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Proposals / New Directions, undated (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Subsidy for Organizing, 1996 (Box-folder 4/21)
  - Memorandum, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Annual Meetings, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 4/23)
  - National Leadership Meeting - 1997 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - New Party National Executive Committee March 20-21, 1999 (Box-folder 4/25)
  - Recent / Current, 2000 (Box-folder 4/26)
  - National Executive Council, 2000 (Box-folder 4/27)
  - New Majority Education Fund, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 4/28)
  - Subsidies, 2001 (Box-folder 4/29)
  - Working Families Party, 2000 (Box-folder 4/30)
  - Portland New Party, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 4/31)
  - Little Rock New Party, 1999 (Box-folder 4/32)
  - Missoula New Party, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 4/33)
  - Proportional Representation, 1996 (Box-folder 4/34)
  - Working Families Party, 2000 (Box-folder 4/35)
  - Correspondence - Election Law, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 4/36)
  - New Majority Education Fund - General, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 4/37)
  - New Majority Education Fund - Foundation, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 4/38)
  - New Majority Education Fund - Labor, Outreach, 2001 (Box-folder 4/39)
  - New Majority Education Fund - Veatch, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 4/40)
  - New Majority Education Fund - Finances, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 4/41)
  - Newsletters - National, 1995-2000; Subseries 1; 0.1 linear feet
    - Summer, 1999 (Box-folder 4/42)
    - Winter, 1998 (Box-folder 4/43)
    - Spring, 1998 (Box-folder 4/44)
    - Winter, 1997 (Box-folder 4/45)
    - Fall, 1997 (Box-folder 4/46)
    - Spring, 1997 (Box-folder 4/47)
    - Winter, 1996 (Box-folder 4/48)
    - Fall, 1996 (Box-folder 4/49)
    - Spring, 1996 (Box-folder 4/50)
    - Winter, 1995 (Box-folder 4/51)
    - Summer, 1995 (Box-folder 4/52)
- Artifacts, undated; Series VI; 2 items
  This series contains two New Party button artifacts
  - New Party buttons, undated (Box-folder 5/3)